<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamacion devised by the Kynges hygnes, with the aduyse of his counsayle, that his subiectes be warned to auoyde (in some c[ase]s) the daunger and penaltie of the statute of Provision and Premunire.</title>
            <author>England. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1533</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.18.e.2[56]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99891715</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99891715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">194296</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 194296)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; D3:1[39])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamacion devised by the Kynges hygnes, with the aduyse of his counsayle, that his subiectes be warned to auoyde (in some c[ase]s) the daunger and penaltie of the statute of Provision and Premunire.</title>
                  <author>England. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Tho. Berthelet regius impressor excudebat. Cum Privilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1533]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Steele notation: late twene extende.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Henry VIII, 1509-1547 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:194296:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A PROCLAMACION DEVISED BY</hi> the kynges hygnes, with the aduyſe of his counſayle, that his ſubiectes be warned to auoyde (in ſome c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s) the daunger and penaltie of the ſtatute of Prouiſion and Premunire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as moche as the vnlauful matrimonie betwene the kynges hyghnes and the lady Katherine princes dowager, late wyfe to prince Arthure, by iuſt wayes and meanes is laufully diſſolued, and a diuorſe and ſeparation had and done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene his ſayde hyghnes and the ſayd lady Katherine, by the moſte reuerende father in god the archbyſhop of Cantur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, legate and primate of al England, and Metropolitane of the ſame: And thervpon the kinges mageſtie hath laufully maried &amp; taken to his wife, after the lawes of the church the ryght high &amp; excellent princes lady Anne now quene of England, &amp; ſhe ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely crowned &amp; anoynted, as appertayneth, to the laude, prayſe, &amp; honour of almyghtie god, the ſuretie of the kynges ſucceſſion and poſterite, and to the great Ioy, comfort, and contentation of all the ſubiectes of this realme. All whiche premiſſes haue groundely proceded and taken their effectes, as well by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men aſſent of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mens of this realme, by auctorite of parlyament, as alſo by the aſſent and determinations of the hole clergie in their ſeuerall conuocations, holden and kepte in bothe prouinces of this realme. And for perfayte and ſure eſtablyſſhement therof, it is enacted amonge other thynges that what ſo euer perſon or perſons, of what eſtate, degree or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition they be of do attempt or procure any maner proces, or do or moue any acte or actes to the lette or derogation of any ſuche procedynges, ſentences, and determynations, as is and haue bene done and hadde as well in and about the ſayde diuorſe, as in the ſolempniſation of the lauful matrimonie had and concluded betwene the kynges hyghneſſe and the ſayde quene Anne: ſhall incurre and rounne in the peynes and penalties compriſed in the ſtatute of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion and premunire made in the .xvi. yere of the late kynge <hi>RICHARDE</hi> the ſeconde, whiche is no leſſe peyne than the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be out of the kynges protection, and their goodes &amp; landes to be forfayted, and their bodies impriſoned at the kynges wyll, as by the ſayde acte more at large is expreſſed. By reaſon wherof and for as moche as the ſayde diuorſe and ſeparation is now had and done, and the kynges hyghneſſe lawfully maryed, as is before reherſed. ¶ <hi>IT IS</hi> therfore euident and manifeſte, that the ſayde lady Katherine ſhulde not frome hens forthe haue or vſe the name, ſtyle, title, or dignitie of Quene of this realme, nor be in any wyſe reputed, taken, accepted, or written by the name of Quene of this realme, but by the name, ſtyle, title, and dignitie of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces dowager, which name ſhe ought to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bicauſe ſhe was laufully &amp; perfectly maried and accoupled with the ſaid prince Arthure And what ſo euer officers, miniſters, bayliffes, receuours, fermours, ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis, kepers of parkes or chaces of the ſayde princes dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or any other perſon or perſons of what aſtate degree or condition they be of, contrary to the premiſſis do name, repute, accept, &amp; write or in any wiſe obey the ſayd lady Katheryn by vertu of any maner of warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or writing to them directed by the name of quene, or attempte do or moue any other acte or actes, thynge or thynges, to the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te or derogation of ſuche doinges and procedynges, as is determined and accomplyſſhed as well for the diſſolution of the ſayd vnlaufull mariage as for the ſolempniſation and confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſayd laufull matrimonie iuſtly finyſſhed and concluded, as is aboue reherſed, ſhall and dothe playnly and manifeſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre &amp; renne in the ſayd great daungers &amp; peynes compriſed &amp; ſpecified in the ſayde acte. In conſideration wherof all be it that the kynge our moſt dradde ſoueraygne lorde nothynge myſtruſteth his louynge ſubiectes for any attempt acte or actes, or any thynge to be done moued or ſpoken by them contrarye to the true meanynge of the ſayde acte, and the due execution and procedynges in the premiſſes: yet neuertheleſſe to thentent that his ſayd humble and louynge ſubiectes ſhall haue playne, open, and manifeſt notice of the greatte perylles, daungers and penalities compriſed and ſpecifyed in the ſayde acte, whereby they maye eſchewe the daungers therof: his maieſtie therfore of his mooſte gratious and benigne goodneſſe, more couaytynge and deſirynge the good obediences and conformities of his ſayde ſubiectis, than to be auaunced and enryched by theyr offences or contemptes, by the aduyſe of his ſayd counſayle hath cauſed this proclamation to be made for a playne ouerture and publication of the premyſſes. Wherby as well all and euery his louynge ſubiectes / as others may (if they wyll) auoyde and eſchewe the ſayde great peynes, daungers, and penalties aboue eſpecified. Whervnto his gracis pleaſure and hyghe commaundement is, that euery perſon from hens forth take good hede and reſpecte / at theyr perylles.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AND</hi> yet neuer the leſſe the kynges moſt gratious pleaſure is, that the ſayde lady Katheryne ſhall be welle vſed obeyed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treted, according to her honour and noble parentage, by the name tytle ſtate and ſtile of princes dowager, as wel by al hir officers ſeruantes and miniſters as alſo by others his humble and louynge ſubiectes in all hir lauful buſyneſſes and affaires: So it extende not in any wyſe contrary to this proclamation.</p>
            <closer>GOD SAVE THE KYNGE.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Berthelet regius impreſſor excudebat. <hi>CVM PRIVILEGIO.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
